ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
TRADE CITY, WARM, IN THE CENTRAL LANDS
（中央諸國，交易都市瓦爾姆）
Okay, let's split up and stock up on things we need for the road.
好，接下來 就分頭採買旅行需要的東西吧
Split up? I'm getting most of the necessities.
分頭？必需品大多是我在買
Food, water, everyday items…
食物、水、日用品…
Mistress Frieren, what are you going to buy?
芙莉蓮大人，您還要買什麼？
Things like herbs…
藥草之類的…
She's making that face that she does when she's hiding something.
她每次擺出那種臉 通常都是有事情瞞著我
I've known Mistress Frieren for a while.
我認識芙莉蓮大人也有一段時間了
I know nothing good will come from this.
這種時候通常都不是什麼好事
She always buys useless things.
她總是會買些用不到的東西
-I couldn't help but buy it. -What is it for?
-忍不住就買了 -這是做什麼用？
-This solution only melts clothing. -Go and return it.
-這是只會讓衣服融化的藥劑 -請拿去退掉
It's a book on the history of magic. It's good to study too.
這是魔法史的書，研讀一下也不錯
Well, I guess that wasn't exactly useless.
我想那個也不算是完全沒用
Well, see you later at the inn.
那晚點在旅店見了
We can't waste our travel expenses.
旅費沒有充裕到可以浪費
I have to keep an eye on her.
得好好看著她才行
An accessory shop?
首飾店？
You went to sleep without drying your hair again.
又沒吹乾頭髮就睡了吧
Jeez…
真是的…
I didn't know she was interested in fashion.
我不知道原來她對時尚有興趣
She's thinking really hard about it.
她很認真在想要買哪個呢
What's up with that face?
那是什麼表情？
I've never seen Mistress Frieren
我從沒見過芙莉蓮大人
thinking that hard about anything.
對什麼事那麼苦惱的表情
That took a long time.
花了不少時間呢
I don't mind if it's accessories.
買首飾我是不介意啦
It's better than weird bones or solutions.
總比買什麼 奇怪的骨頭或是藥劑好多了
Maybe I should get started on my shopping.
我差不多也該開始採買了
Is there a good dessert place around here?
這附近有好吃的甜點店嗎？
Now that's not fair!
這個就太不公平了！
There's an underground bar over there, so you should ask them.
這種事去那邊的地下酒館問比較好
Thanks.
謝謝
Even I haven't eaten anything sweet for months!
我都好幾個月沒吃過甜點了！
This is the place?
就是這裡嗎？
Is there a good dessert place around here?
這附近有好吃的甜點店嗎？
Uh, obviously this isn't the place to ask about desserts!
不是吧 這裡顯然不是問甜點店的地方！
A dessert place?
甜點店？
Are you kidding me?
妳這是小看我嗎？
This town has a ton of great desserts!
鎮上有超多超好吃的甜點店！
We can tell you about any store out there.
我們可以如數家珍地報給妳聽
They actually know?
他們真的知道啊？
You look tough, but you're in the know?
你們看起來很粗曠 不過知道的不少嘛？
Desserts are a source of energy for adventurers like us.
甜點可是我們這種冒險家的動力來源
They were adventurers?
他們是冒險家？
They look much worse than just "tough guys."
這看起來哪裡只是粗曠而已啊
They're too scary!
很恐怖好嗎！
Bye!
拜！
Is she going to a dessert shop?
接下來要去甜點店嗎？
Oh? This is…
咦？這邊…
the direction our inn is located. Is she going back?
是往旅店的方向啊，她要回去了？
Oh!
對喔！
I haven't done my shopping at all.
我什麼都還沒買
You're late.
太慢了
I'm sorry.
對不起
Well, whatever. Put down your things.
算了，東西放下吧
Let's go eat something sweet for once.
我們偶爾也去吃個甜點吧
What a great view. No wonder they recommended it.
景色真棒，難怪他們會推薦這裡
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉蓮大人
I'm sorry I doubted you.
對不起，我懷疑了您
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
Nothing…
沒什麼…
Choose whatever you want.
喜歡什麼隨便點
Do we have enough money?
我們的旅費夠嗎？
I have my savings.
我有私房錢喔
She had savings?
原來有私房錢啊
Mistress Frieren, what will you order?
芙莉蓮大人，您要點什麼？
Let's see… Today I feel like…
看看喔，今天就我的心情來看…
Merkur pudding, right?
是水星布丁吧？
Let me guess, you feel like Merkur pudding?
就妳的心情來看，是水星布丁吧？
How do you know?
你怎麼知道？
How long do you think we've been traveling together?
妳以為我們一起旅行多久了？
I can tell.
自然看得出來
I don't know anything about you guys.
我對你們就一點都不了解
Then I guess I'll try my best to get you to know me.
這樣的話，我也盡力 讓妳努力了解我們吧
By the way, my favorite food is ruf-omelet.
對了，我最愛的食物是露芙蛋包飯
I like grapes. The sourer the better.
我喜歡葡萄，越酸越好
-I like-- -Alcohol, right?
-我喜歡… -是酒吧？
I know that, Corrupt Priest.
這個我知道喔，酒肉僧侶
That's not something to blush about.
這沒有什麼好害羞的吧
Isn't it bad that a priest drinks so much that everyone knows.
作為僧侶居然愛喝酒 愛喝到大家都知道，不是很糟糕嗎？
I'm sorry, Fern.
對不起，費倫
Why are you apologizing?
為什麼您要道歉呢？
I don't know anything about you, Fern.
我對妳一點也不了解，費倫
So I didn't know
所以我不知道
what kind of things you like.
妳喜歡什麼東西
I had forgotten that today is my birthday.
說起來，今天是我生日呢
What a pretty hair accessory.
好漂亮的髮飾
Thank you very much. I'm really happy.
真的很感謝您，我真的很開心
You are?
真的嗎？
It seems like you are horrible at taking hints,
芙莉蓮大人實在非常遲鈍
so I'll be straightforward.
所以我就直說了
I am extremely happy that you tried
您努力想要了解我的心情
to get to know me.
讓我開心到不能自己
Even though I only tried?
就只是因為我努力想要了解妳嗎？
Mistress Frieren, you really don't understand people's feelings, do you?
芙莉蓮大人 您真的都不懂別人的感情吧？
-Let's leave soon. -Okay.
-差不多該走了 -好
By the way, Mistress Frieren,
話說回來，芙莉蓮大人
is there a goal to this journey?
這趟旅途有什麼目標嗎？
Not really. I'm traveling as a hobby to collect spells.
沒什麼目標，純粹是出於 我收集魔法的興趣啟程的
But
不過
I want to revisit
可以的話
the traces from my adventure with Himmel and the crew as much as I can.
我想重新拜訪 以往跟欣梅爾他們冒險的痕跡
Before they fade away.
在這些痕跡風化之前
That must be very important
那對芙莉蓮大人而言
to you, Mistress Frieren.
是很重要的事物吧
I don't know.
我不知道
That's why I want to know.
所以我想要弄清楚
Jeez, I can't believe you're taller than me now.
話說，妳竟然長得比我高了
I am already 16 years old, after all. I'm a lady now.
畢竟我已經十六歲了，是個大姐姐了
A lady…
大姐姐…
We're eating the same things and yet…
不是都吃一樣的東西嗎？
What a mystery.
真是不可思議
27 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的27年後）
GRÖSSE FOREST IN THE CENTRAL LANDS
（中央諸國，古列賽森林）
You've gotten used to using defensive magic.
妳已經熟悉防禦魔法了
Now, let's put it into practical use.
好，那就來應用看看
I attacked the gaps in your defense.
我瞄準了妳防禦的空隙攻擊
If it wasn't training, you'd be dead.
如果不是模擬戰的話，妳已經死了
Well then…
那麼…
How will you tackle this?
妳要怎麼對付這種攻擊？
Like this.
這樣
I see.
是嗎？
Can you handle this?
那這個妳能應付嗎？
That's all for today.
今天就到這裡吧
Defensive magic is powerful,
防禦魔法雖然強大
but it eats up a lot of mana.
但是也會消耗大量魔力
If you keep using it in wide ranges,
如果持續大範圍使用的話
you'll run out of mana in less than a minute.
不用一分鐘就會消耗完魔力
So, the correct way is to activate it in sections, right as the attack lands?
所以應該要在攻擊命中時 進行瞬間的小範圍防禦？
That's right.
沒錯
Up we go.
走
We've only been practicing defensive magic.
都是防禦魔法的練習呢
It's directly related to your chances of survival.
因為這直接影響妳在戰場上的存活率
That's true.
確實是
You can stop almost all offensive magic with defensive magic.
光靠防禦魔法 就能抵擋絕大多數的攻擊魔法
It's so powerful, it's mind-boggling.
強大到讓人難以置信
Fern,
費倫
you didn't read the history of magic book, did you?
妳沒有讀那本魔法史的書吧？
Magic involves more than just practicing it.
魔法可不是只有實踐而已
I guess I need to read it to you as a bedtime story.
果然睡前沒讀給妳聽是不行的
I'll read it myself.
我會自己讀的
I'm not a child.
又不是小孩子了
This is our destination?
這裡就是目的地？
Are you collecting another weird spell?
又要收集什麼奇怪的魔法嗎？
No, not this time.
不，這次不是
It depends on the weather.
還要看天公作不作美
I guess so.
我想也是
Can I ask you about something?
抱歉，能打聽一點事情嗎？
-It's an elf. -With white hair?
-是精靈 -白頭髮的？
Are you Mistress Frieren by any chance?
難道您是芙莉蓮大人？
How do you know me?
你怎麼會認識我？
You want to know the location of the sealed Qual, right?
您是要找庫瓦爾的封印之地吧？
I'll show you the way.
我帶您過去
Qual?
庫瓦爾？
Qual, the Elder Sage of Corruption.
腐敗的賢老庫瓦爾
He is a demon who committed
八十年前在這片土地上
atrocities in this land 80 years ago.
無惡不作、橫行霸道的魔族
However, Himmel the Hero
後來勇者欣梅爾一行人
and his party sealed him away for us.
把他封印在這裡了
That seal is going to break soon, so I came to eliminate him.
封印就快失效了，所以我過來討伐他
How did you know that though?
是說你怎麼知道這麼多？
I didn't tell anyone about this.
這件事我誰都沒有說過
Until about 30 years ago,
直到大概三十年前
Master Himmel would visit the village almost every year.
欣梅爾大人幾乎每年都會來村裡看看
He said it was to check on how the seal was holding up.
他說是來確認封印的狀態
Such a nice guy, as usual.
真是一如既往的好人呢
He would talk about you too, Mistress Frieren.
他也提起過您喔，芙莉蓮大人
He called you "a cold-hearted person who never comes to visit."
他說您很無情，絕對不會過來看看的
Isn't she cold?
很沒人情味吧？
That is cold.
是很沒人情味
Well excuse me.
還真是抱歉喔
But
不過
she's not cold-hearted enough to abandon the village.
她還沒有無情到會拋下這個村子不管
She'll appear by the time the seal is about to break.
封印快解除的時候，她就會出現了
That is what he told me.
他是這麼跟我說的
I see.
這樣啊
This is it?
就是這個了嗎？
It's pretty vulnerable.
封印已經很不穩定了
Let's unseal Qual tomorrow
明天就解封庫瓦爾
and get rid of him.
然後收拾他吧
Mistress Frieren, you sealed Qual, right?
芙莉蓮大人 是您封印了庫瓦爾，對吧？
Is there a reason why you did that?
封印他有什麼理由嗎？
Simply because Qual was strong.
只是因為庫瓦爾太強了
We couldn't win against him.
我們打不過他
Qual was one of the best mages in the Demon King's army.
庫瓦爾是魔王軍中數一數二的魔法史
Zoltraak.
除魔魔法
That's the first piercing magic in history which Qual developed.
那傢伙開發了史上第一種貫穿魔法
It pierced through the defensive magic of humans
是種能夠穿透人類防禦的魔法
as well as magic-resistant equipment.
連人類的魔法防禦裝備也無法抵擋
It's a spell that directly destroys the body.
那種魔法會直接摧毀人體
In this region, 40% of adventurers
根據紀錄，這片土地上
and 70% of mages
有四成冒險者跟七成魔法使
were killed by Zoltraak, according to records.
都死於這個除魔魔法
That's way too powerful.
那簡直是強大過頭了
That's right. It was too powerful. Much too powerful.
沒錯，太強了，強得過頭了
That is exactly why its power backfired on him.
他也因為這份強大而栽了跟頭
What do you mean?
請問這是什麼意思？
You really didn't read the history of magic book.
妳真的都沒讀我給妳的魔法史書
Maybe you need story time after all.
果然還是需要我讀給妳聽吧
I'll read it now.
我現在就讀
No, it's fine.
不用了，沒關係
Getting enough sleep is more important.
現在好好睡覺更重要
You'll find out tomorrow anyway.
反正明天妳就會知道了
I'll break the seal.
我要解除封印了
Don't let your guard down.
不要大意了
Long time no see, Frieren.
好久不見了，芙莉蓮
How many years has it been?
過了多少年了啊？
Eighty years.
八十年
Merely 80 years?
才八十年嗎？
To us, at least.
至少對我們來說是這樣
What about the Demon King?
魔王大人呢？
We killed him.
殺掉了
I see.
這樣啊
Well then,
那麼…
I guess I should get revenge.
就讓老朽來報仇吧
Fern, activate defensive magic in front of you.
費倫，在前方展開防禦魔法
Zoltraak!
除魔魔法！
That's surprising.
真令人意外
You resisted Zoltraak?
竟然能擋住除魔魔法？
That must be a very advanced defensive spell.
真是相當高水準的防禦魔法
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉蓮大人
what is going on?
這是怎麼回事？
That was ordinary offensive magic.
剛剛那是一般攻擊魔法吧
That just now was Zoltraak.
那就是除魔魔法
The one he developed.
他開發出來的
A spell to kill humans.
殺人魔法
Qual,
庫瓦爾
your magic was too powerful.
你的魔法太強大
After you were sealed,
在你被封印之後
mages from around the continent
大陸的魔法使們
studied and analyzed Zoltraak.
就開始研究並解析除魔魔法
In just a few years,
不過數年的時間
Zoltraak was incorporated into the framework of mankind's magic.
除魔魔法就被納入人類體系的魔法中
And they developed powerful defensive magic
並且根據新的防禦術式
based on a new defensive spell.
開發出威力更強的防禦魔法
The level of magic-resistance of equipment has improved too.
防禦魔法的裝備耐受性也改良了
Zoltraak is no longer a spell that can kill humans.
除魔魔法已不再是殺人的魔法
Now, it's called ordinary offensive magic.
現在人們稱它為一般攻擊魔法
Apparently, 80 years is a very long time for humans.
看來八十年 對人類來說是相當長的時間呢
Qual,
庫瓦爾
if you behave, I will kill you with mercy.
如果你束手就擒的話 我會讓你死得乾淨俐落點
Interesting…
原來如此…
Very interesting.
原來是這樣
It synchronizes with the offensive magic
原來是跟攻擊魔法同調
and disperses the power, huh?
然後讓威力分散開來嗎？
What a complicated spell.
真是複雜的術式
I bet it uses up a lot of mana as well.
想必要消耗巨大的魔力吧
He realized the weakness of defensive magic.
他發現防禦魔法的弱點了
Fern, you can handle it, right?
費倫，妳能對付吧？
Yes.
可以
I already saw this during training.
練習時就已經看過了
Then shield me as well.
那就連我一起保護
Oh, you can fly? Interesting!
妳會飛？真有趣！
Zoltraak.
除魔魔法
Frieren…
芙莉蓮…
that's my… magic…
那是…老朽的魔法…
-We're so glad! -Thank you so much.
-太好了！ -太感謝了
Now we can live in peace.
這麼一來，我們能安心度日了
Hey, that hat…
話說那頂帽子…
This?
這頂嗎？
In this region,
這一帶
the sun still shines brightly at this time of year,
每年這個時節，太陽都很烈
so it's needed for farming.
所以下田務農一定要戴它
I've seen this somewhere.
我在哪裡看過這個
You…
你…
You're the brat who flipped my skirt.
是當年偷掀我裙子的臭小鬼
What are you doing, you damn brat?!
臭小鬼，你在幹什麼！
I'll kill you! I wanted to see too!
我宰了你！我都還沒看過呢！
You shouldn't kill him.
不可以殺人
Come on, I'll show you mine.
我的給你看就好了
Wow…
哇賽…
You are still alive?
你還活著啊？
Thanks to you, I feel like I can live even longer.
托您的福，我想我可以再活久一點
I'm glad I believed Master Himmel and waited for you.
我一直相信欣梅爾大人的話在此等您
They were all thanking you, Mistress Frieren.
他們全都很感謝您，芙莉蓮大人
It wasn't directed toward me.
他們感謝的對象不是我
The people of this village believed in Himmel.
這個村子的人一直相信著欣梅爾
I don't know the details,
雖然我不明白其中過往
but I'm sure Master Himmel believed in you.
但我認為欣梅爾大人一定是相信著您
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Nothing.
沒什麼
-I felt pity. -It's more convenient that way.
-我覺得太可憐了 -存在的話就方便多了
-Is she really from primitive times? -No sad stories!
-她真的是從原始時代活過來的嗎？ -不要說這麼沉重的話題！
-It was a long time ago. -I reached it.
-已經是很久以前的事了 -我抵達了靈魂安息的所在
"The land where souls rest."
靈魂長眠之地
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻